

□ (+45) 60 90 60 12 | Serik@i-solution.de | 🛪 www.erikkusch.com | 🖫 ErikKusch | 💆 KuschErik | 🛅 Kusch Erik | Rº Erik Kusch

Research Profile _

I am a macroecologist specialised in remote sensing applications and spatio-temporal analyses of biodiversity dynamics. I use quantitative tools to research ecosystem resilience, vegetation dynamics, and patterns of landscape-scale biodiversity to understand past, present, and future trajectories of natural ecosystems.

Education

PhD in Biology; Specialisation on Ecoinformatics and Biodiversity

Aarhus, Denmark Oxford, United Kingdom

AARHUS UNIVERSITY & OXFORD UNIVERSITY

01/2020 - PRESENT

Species association and interaction networks;

Extinction debt consequences

7th Edition Species Distribution Modelling Course

Évora, Portugal

University of Évora, Science Retreats

26/04/2021 - 02/05/2021

Theoretical underpinnings of ecological niche models

Strengths and limitations of ecological niche models in the context of different uses

Design an ecological niche modelling study for a variety of uses

Ecological niche modelling using SDM R.

Modelling Challenges for Mountain Ecosystems

Hamburg, Germany

23/02/2020 - 28/02/2020

University of Hamburg

Addressing issues of limited data availability, data bias of unknown magnitude, poor availability of ref-

erence studies

Statistical Modelling of Climate Parameters

Modelling the Ecological Niche of a Treeline Species.

Bergen, Norway

University of Bergen (UIB)

iB)

вегдеп, *Norway* 08/2017 - 08/2019

08/2019 Graduation from UiB (M.Sc., overall grade: A)

08/2018 - 07/2019 Master's Thesis at UiB & Nansen Environmental and Remote Sensing Center:

"Inferring Vegetation Memory from Remote Sensing Data and identifying Causal

Links to Plant Function" (grade: First/A)

M.Sc. in Biology; Specialisation on Biodiversity, Ecology and Evolution

Plant Functional Traits Course 3

Wayquecha Biological Station, Peru

University of Bergen (UiB), University of Arizona (UoA)

Introduction to plant functional trait based ecology;

Collecting plant functional trait data in the field;

Developing data management skills;

Assessing the impact of fire regimes on the Puna grasslands of the Peruvian Andes

Bayesian Modelling Summer School

Lygra, Norway

Norwegian University of Life Sciences (NMBU)

25/10/2017 - 29/10/2017

08/03/2018 - 24/03/2018

Introduction to the concepts of Bayesian statistics (priors, likelihoods, etc.); Sampling methods (Markov Chain Monte Carlo, rejection sampling, etc.);

Bayesian modelling and hierarchical Bayesian models

B.Sc. in Biology

Dresden, Germany / Bergen, Norway

10/2013 - 07/2017

TECHNICAL UNIVERSITY DRESDEN (TUD) / UNIVERSITY OF BERGEN (UIB)
07/2017 Graduation from TUD (Diploma/B.Sc., overall grade: 1.7)

09/2016 - 02/2017 Bachelor's Thesis at UiB (via ERASMUS):

"Remote Sensing And Predicting Shifts In Biome Distribution And Resilience Using

NDVI Data" (grade: First/A)

08/2015 - 12/2015 Studies at UiB (via ERASMUS)

Experience

Research station co-manager

Scoraig, Scotland
06/2019 - PRESENT

SPATIAL AND POPULATION ECOLOGY, UNIVERSITY OF GLASGOW

- Scientific consultant/advisor for selected course activities on-sight
- · Visitor introduction and orientation
- · Visitor management
- · Outreach to local communities
- · Research station maintenance
- · Converting croft to research station

Research fellow Bergen, Norway

ECOLOGICAL AND ENVIRONMENTAL CHANGE RESEARCH GROUP, UNIVERSITY OF BERGEN

- Global dryland vegetation memory research
- Funded via Fast-Track-Initiative programme (see Honours & Awards)

Research and Teaching Assistant

Leipzig, Germany

09/2019 - 12/2019

08/2017 - 08/2019; 03/2017 - 04/2017

BEHAVIOURAL ECOLOGY RESEARCH GROUP, UNIVERSITY OF LEIPZIG

- Analysing primate odour profiles
- Assessing a variety of statistical methods for analytical power in identifying odour effects
- Generating data with various implemented odour effects on which to test the methods

Research and Outreach Assistant

Nagata/Inuyama, Japan

07/2018

PRIMATE RESEARCH CENTRE, UNIVERSITY OF KYOTO

- Collecting faecal & recording behaviour samples of Japanese macaques
- Analysing behavioural interactions via network analyses
- Creating a text-based adventure game about behavioural studies

Research Assistant Wilhelmshaven, Germany

GERMAN CENTRE FOR MARINE BIODIVERSITY RESEARCH (DZMB), SENCKENBERG GROUP

05/2017 - 07/2017

- Sorting benthos samples and meiofauna taxa
- $\bullet \ \ \text{Researching trophic networks between Antarctic meio- and macrobenthos over time via stable isotope analyses}$

Student Assistant Dresden, Germany

BOTANICAL INSTITUTE, TECHNICAL UNIVERSITY DRESDEN (TUD)

05/2016 - 08/2016; 02/2015 - 08/2015

• Mapping distribution of moss species throughout the Elbsandsteingebirge

Student Assistant Dresden, Germany

ZOOLOGICAL COLLECTION, TECHNICAL UNIVERSITY DRESDEN (TUD)

04/2016 - 05/2016; 11/2013 - 08/2015

• Restructuring the collection & carrying out a regular stocktaking

Ranger & Tour Guide Saxony, Germany

NATIONAL PARK SAXON-BOHEMIAN SWISS

04/2016 - 06/2016

• Conducting programmes concerning environmental and biodiversity education

MAY 17, 2021 ERIK KUSCH · CURRICULUM VITAE 2

Teaching & Supervision Activity

Author & Lecturer: Excursions into Biostatistics

☐ GitHub Repository

SEMINAR SERIES

A diverse range of talks concerning biostatistics including (but not limited to) overviews of classification and regression methods as well as their application in R, statistical significance and the p-value conundrum, model selection and validation, coding practices, and basic statistical terminology.

Author & Lecturer: An Introduction to Biostatistics Using R

☐ GitHub Repository

TALK SERIES

An introductory biostatistics course for undergraduate and graduate students consisting of 13 lectures which provide an overview of the fundamentals of basic biostatistical methods and their application in R. The theoretical aspects of the course series are supplemented with hands-on exercises on a simulated data set of house sparrow morphology across the globe to simulate a coherent research project throughout the duration of the course.

Teaching Assistant

Aarhus University

APPLIED STATISTICS 22/03/2021 - 14/05/2021

• Assistance for B.Sc. students in solving exercises in the R and RCommander software environments

Teaching Assistant

Aarhus University

STATISTICAL AND GEOSPATIAL MODELLING

03/09/2020 - 18/12/2020

- Assistance for M.Sc. students in solving exercises in the R software environment
- Grading of student assignments

Teaching Assistant Aarhus University

GEOSPATIAL INFORMATION SYSTEMS

27/10/2020 - 18/12/2020

- Assistance for B.Sc. and M.Sc. students in solving exercises pertaining to GIS software
- Grading of student assignments

Author Aarhus University

BIOLOGICAL RESEARCH IN THEORY AND PRAXIS (BFTP)

- Project resources for biome classification analyses from NDVI data
- RMarkdown introductions to spatial ecology & k-cluster analyses

Instructor & Advisor

Aarhus University

ECOINFORMATICS & BIODIVERSITY MASTERS SEMINARS (EBMS)

03/02/2021 - 05/05/2021

- Feedback to student presentations
- Resources, presentations, and advisorship concerning biostatistics
- Arrangements for invited speaker presentations

Extracurricular Activity _____

Member: Statistics Journal Club

Glasgow, Scotland

University of Glasgow

10/03/2021 - PRESENT

• Discussion of recent publications in the field of biostatistics

Member: Spatial Shared-Interest Group

Glasgow, Scotland

University of Glasgow

10/03/2021 - PRESENT

· Discussion of recent publications, methodological developments, and ongoing research in the field of spatial ecology

Leader: AU Bayes Study Group

AARHUS UNIVERSITY

Aarhus, Denmark

19/11/2020 - PRESENT

- Introduction to the concepts of Bayesian statistics (priors, likelihoods, etc.)
- Sampling methods (Markov Chain Monte Carlo, rejection sampling, etc.)
- Bayesian modelling and hierarchical Bayesian models
- Using published literature as tutorials

Member: Bayes Study Group

University of Bergen

Bergen, Norway 09/2018 - 12/2019

- Understanding Bayesian statistics in theory and practice
- Using published literature as tutorials

Member: EECRG Reading Group

University of Bergen

Bergen, Norway 10/2017 - 12/2019

- · Proof-reading other students'/researchers' writing
- · Providing own writing to be proof-read

Tutor: BiOrakel Team Bergen, Norway

CENTRE OF EXCELLENCE IN BIODIVERSITY EDUCATION (BIOCEED), UNIVERSITY OF BERGEN

08/2017 - 07/2018

- Answering study-topic related questions from students
- Tutoring students on how to use statistical programmes
- Explaining how to do proper referencing

Core Member: Students Council of Biology Studies at the TUD

Dresden, Germany

TECHNICAL UNIVERSITY OF DRESDEN

• Student coordinator of exchange programs

10/2013 - 10/2015

Honours & Grants & Awards ____

SCHOLARSHIPS & GRANTS

10/2020	Scholarship for Academically Excellent Students , Frands Christian Frantsen's Scholarship	Aarhus, Denmark
03/2019	Funding for Particularly Talented Students, Lina Asbjørnsens Stipendiefond	Bergen, Norway
02/2019	Fast-Track-Initiative Funding, FTI, Bjerknessenteret	Bergen, Norway
03/2018 - 08/2019	Project Grant, L. Meltzers Høyskolefond	Bergen, Norway
08/2019		bergen, Norway
03/2018 -		Bonn, Germany
08/2019	Schotarship, German Academic Schotarship Foundation (Studienstilling des deutschen volkes)	bonn, Germany
Awards		

10/2019 Best Poster: Student and Early Career Researcher, International Society for Ecological Modelling	ng Salzburg, Austria
10/2019 Modeller's Choice Poster Award, International Society for Ecological Modelling	Salzburg, Austria

Talks _

KrigR - The R Package

Hamburg, Germany Sydney, Australia

25/03/2021

SPEAKER, AK KLIMA INTERIMSTREFFEN

• Introducing the KrigR R Package

- Era5(-Land) download functionality
- Geostatistical downscaling (kriging) of spatial products

26/03/2021

KrigR - Climate Data For Your Spatial Study

INVITED SPEAKER, SALGO TEAM, UNIVERSITY OF OXFORD

SPEAKER, INTERNATIONAL STATISTICAL ECOLOGY CONFERENCE 2020

- Introducing the KrigR R Package
- Climate data products
- Era5(-Land) download functionality
- · Geostatistical downscaling (kriging) of spatial products
- Kriging pitfalls and recommendations

Remote Sensing Vegetation Memory as a Proxy of Resilience and Demographies

INVITED SPEAKER, SALGO TEAM, UNIVERSITY OF OXFORD

- · Linking resilience components and vegetation memory
- Using state-of-the-art climate reanalysis data sets
- Global generalisations of vegetation memory across dryland regions
- · Linking remote sensed resilience proxies of vegetation communities with vegetation demography

Identifying ecological-memory patterns in drylands using remote sensing and state-of-the-art climate-reanalysis products

INVITED SPEAKER, ECOSYSTEM RESEARCH GROUP, UNIVERSITY OF OXFORD

SPEAKER, INTERNATIONAL SOCIETY FOR ECOLOGICAL MODELLING CONFERENCE 2019

INVITED SPEAKER, ECOINFORMATICS AND BIODIVERSITY RESEARCH GROUP, UNIVERSITY OF AARHUS

- · Use of statistical downscaling approaches of state-of-the art climate reanalysis products in macroecolgy
- · Metric of cross-community vegetation resilience expressed through vegetation memory patterns

Rmarkdown - Manuscript Workflow Revisited

INVITED SPEAKER, BEHAVIOURAL ECOLOGY GROUP, UNIVERSITÄT LEIPZIG

- · Introduction to Rmarkdown and its capabilities
- Latex-based compilation of manuscripts and R codes via Rmarkdown

Statistical Significance in Biology - Conventions, Abstractions, and the Future

Invited Speaker, Behavioural Ecology Research Group, Universität Leipzig

- · Overview to the reproducibility crisis in contemporary research
- Guidelines to proper statistical conduct in biological sciences

Spatial Patterns of Plant Performance

INVITED SPEAKER, BIO DAY, UNIVERSITETET I BERGEN

- Metrics of plant performance through time-series analyses
- Explaining plant response to climate events through ecosystem function

Inferring Vegetation Memory from Remote Sensing Data

INVITED SPEAKER, SPATIAL ECOLOGY GROUP, UNIVERSITY OF GLASGOW

- Use of state-of-the art climate reanalysis products in macroecolgy
- · Spatio-temporal approaches to ecosystem resilience through vegetation memory on regional scales

Aktivurlaub als Hämophilie-Patient

Invited Speaker, Central German Conference of the German Haemophilia Agency (DHG)

- Why to keep active as a haemophilia patient
- How to organise travels as a haemophiliac
- Recommendations of activities that are permissible for haemophiliacs

Oxford, United Kingdom Sydney, Australia

> 18/06/2020 25/06/2020

16/10/2019

Oxford, United Kingdom

Oxford, United Kingdom Salzburg, Austria Aarhus, Denmark

15/10/2019

04/10/2019

06/09/2019

Leipzig, Germany

18/06/2019

Laineia Carnaga

Leipzig, Germany 18/06/2019

Bergen, Norway 15/03/2019

Glasgow, Scotland

09/01/2019

03/01/2013

Leipzig, Sachsen, Germany

03/03/2015

Posters

Intrinsic vegetation memory as a proxy of engineering resilience may be an oversimplification

POSTER AUTHOR AND PRESENTER, BJERKNES CENTRE FOR CLIMATE RESEARCH ANNUAL MEETING 2019

Bergen, Norway Salzburg, Austria Sydney, Australia

16/09/2019

03/10/2019

25/06/2020

 ${\tt POSTER\, AUTHOR\, AND\, PRESENTER, INTERNATIONAL\, SOCIETY\, FOR\, ECOLOGICAL\, MODELLING\, CONFERENCE\, 2019}$

POSTER AUTHOR AND PRESENTER, INTERNATIONAL STATISTICAL ECOLOGY CONFERENCE 2020

- Understanding resilience components through vegetation memory characteristics
- Using state-of-the-art climate reanalysis data sets
- · Making policy decisions based on vegetation memory

The role of meiofauna in benthic functioning - a question of time

Corpus Christi, Texas, USA Rostock, Germany

CO-AUTHOR OF DFG SPP 1158 ANTARCTIC RESEARCH REPORT COLLOQUIUM

03/2018

· Research considering trophic networks between Antarctic meio- and macrobenthos over time via stable isotope analyses

Memberships and Affiliations

- · Research Collaborator with the SalGo Team at Oxford University
- · Research Station Co-Manager with Spatial and Population Ecology, University of Glasgow
- · Member of the International Society For Ecological Modelling (ISEM)
- · Member of the International Biogeography Society (IBS)
- · Alumni of the German Academic Scholarship Foundation (Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes)
- · Member of the British Ecological Society (BES)
- · Member of the German Hemophilia Association (DHG)
- · Member of the DNT Norge (Norwegian Trekking Association)
- · Member of the International Youth Hostelling Organization (DJH)

Activities and Interests _____

- · Hiking and mountaineering
- · Rock climbing
- · Sports (endurance and strength training)
- · Photography
- · Archery
- · Choir singing

References _____

References are available on request.